Guide to the New York State Library School Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
New York State Library School Records
1887-1967.
New York State Library. School.
33 linear ft. (ca. 32,200 items in 91 boxes and 2 oversize flat boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4079161
History
Scope and Content
The incomplete records of the New York State Library School (NYSLS), Albany, 1890-1911. Included are diploma lists, grade sheets, examination questions, examination questions with corresponding set of students' answers, pass cards, senior certificate lists, an admissions application, entrance examinations, curriculum materials, and some documents for the class of 1890. Also, records of the New York State Library School Association, Incorporated. In addition to letters from such prominent American librarians as Katharine L. Sharp, Joseph Wheeler, Ralph Munn, and James I. Wyer, there are minutes, reports, memoranda, and printed documents, including the Association's constitution. There is a scrapbook of blanks and forms used in the executive departments of U.S. libraries in 1893, mounted by the N.Y. State Library School for the American Library Association World's Columbian Exposition Comparative Library Exhibit (Chicago, 1893). Also, files of the school consisting of course materials, exams, publications of the School, student records, admission files, class lists and rankings, and some related correspondence.
1992 Addition: Administrative records of the school consisting of correspondence, student records, including card files containing the citation of bibliographies and theses submitted by students, as well as "community studies" covering the libraries of various regions of the world. There are also records of the NYSLS Association consisting of correspondence, minutes of meetings, constitution, financial records and a selection of photographs of prominent librarians, 1886-1967.
Arrangement
The records are divided into four series:
Series I
Series II: 1981 Addition
Series III: 1992 Addition
Series IV: 2005 Addition
Subjects
World's Columbian Exposition (1893 :--Chicago, Ill.); American Library Association.; Sharp, Katharine L.; Wheeler, Joseph Lewis, 1884-; Munn, Ralph.; Wyer, James I.; Library education--New York (State); Library schools--New York (State)--Albany.; Librarians--United States.; Librarians--Societies, etc.; Applications.; Bibliographies.; Card files.; Constitutions.; Diplomas.; Examinations.; Forms.; Lists.; Memorandums.; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Notes.; Photographs.; Portraits.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Seals.; College teachers.; Librarians.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
Material in Boxes 1 and 2 is charred and has been microfilmed. Reader must use microfilm. Originals are not to be used unless the particular frame or frames needed are illegible.
The scrapbook in Box 4 is charred and is very fragile.
Acquisition
1971 M-71 Columbia University School of Library Service Gift
1992 M-1992 Photographs & printed misc. School of Library Service Transfer
Alternate Formats
Material in Boxes 1 and 2 is charred; Microfilm available.
Related Material-- at Columbia
New York State Library School Register is in the K. Brown collection, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Finding aid in respository and online.
- Series I
  - American Library Association World’s Columbia Exposition Comparative Library Exhibit--Blanks and Forms Used in the Executive Departments of the Various Libraries in the United States, 1893 (Box 4)
    (1 Scrapbook. Scrapbook was charred by fire and is very fragile.)
  - Application for Admission (Box 3)
  - Change in Curriculum (Box 3)
  - Class of 1890--Minutes, Registers, etc. (Box 3)
  - Curriculum Materials for Cataloging and Acquisitions (Box 3)
  - Diplomas arranged by faculty and class (Box 1)
  - Diplomas arranged in chronological order (Box 1)
  - Entrance Questions (Box 3)
  - Exam Questions, 1890-1892 (Box 3)
  - Examination Questions (Box 1)
  - Examination Questions and Students’ Answers
    - #1-12 (Box 1)
    - #13-28 (Box 1)
  - Grade Sheets, (6 Folders) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - New York State Library School
    - Association, Inc. (Box 3)
    - Advisory Board Reports, 1907-1913 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1895 (Box 3)
      - 1906-1926 (Box 3)
      - 1927 (Box 3)
      - 1928 (Box 3)
      - 1929 (Box 3)
    - Minutes
      - 1894-1923 (Box 3)
      - 1924-1928 (Box 3)
      - 1928-1931 (Box 3)
    - Printed Documents, including Constitution (Box 3)
    - Reports, Memos (Box 3)
  - Pass Cards (Box 2)
- Series II: 1981 Addition
  - Association of the New York State Library School Files, 1945-1957 (Box 53-54)
  - Documentary History
    - Chronological File
      (Course materials with some related correspondence)
      - 1887-1911 (Box 5-8)
        (Box 5 contains general files; the rest of the files are arranged chronologically by semester and sub-arranged by course title)
      - 1887-1911 (Box 9)
      - 1911-1915
        - 1911-1912 (Box 9)
        - 1912-1913 (Box 10)
        - 1914-1915 (Box 11)
      - 1915-1921
        - 1915-1917 (Box 12)
        - 1917-1919 (Box 13)
        - 1919-1921 (Box 14-15)
      - 1921-1926
        - 1921-1922 (Box 16)
        - 1923-1926 (Box 17)
        - 1924-1925 (Box 18-19)
        - 1925-1926 (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous Files
      (Unsorted; partially identified)
      - Bookbinding (Box 35-36)
      - Course Materials (Box 21, 38-41)
      - Library Buildings (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous Unsorted (Box 24-29, 31-33, 37)
        (Box 24 includes Faculty Minutes Book, Volume 3, 1911-1924. Volumes 1-2 were destroyed in the 1911 fire.)
      - Practice Work: Library Buildings (Box 22)
        (Reports on tours of northeastern libraries)
      - Students’ Notes (Box 34)
      - Student Ranking Sheets (Box 30)
  - Edna M. Sanderson Files
    (Registrar at NYSLS, 1905-1919; Vice-Director, 1919-1926)
    - Correspondence (Box 49)
    - Course Materials (Box 49-52)
  - Student Records
    - Aik-Coo (Box 42)
    - Cor-Has (Box 43)
    - Hat-Mac (Box 44)
    - Mag-Rin (Box 45)
    - Rob-Tha (Box 46)
    - Tho-Yo (Box 47)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 48)
- Series III: 1992 Addition
  - Administrative Records and Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 70)
    (Includes correspondence with Melvil Dewey and the text of the school song)
  - Alumni Collection
    - Correspondence (Box 78)
    - Lectures (Box 78)
    - Memorabilia (Box 78)
    - Register (Box 78)
  - Association Records
    - Minutes of the Annual Meeting, 1924-1926 (Box 71)
    - Constitution (Box 72)
    - List of Officers (Box 72)
    - Minutes of Directors’ Meetings, 1926-1966 (Box 72)
    - Treasurer’s Reports (Box 73)
    - Scholarships, Loans, Insurance, and Bequests (Box 73)
    - Sample of Letterhead (Box 74)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence to 1962 (Box 74)
    - Newsletters, 1926-1927 (Box 74)
    - Biscoe Photograph (Box 74)
    - Class of 1890 Photograph (Box 74)
    - Aluminum Seal of the Association (Box 75)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1967 (Box 75)
    - Alumni Address Lists (Box 75)
  - Card Files
    - Two Card Files (Box 77)
      (Once file contains the alphabetized records of bibliographies and theses submitted for graduation requirements for NYSLS through 1902. The second file contains "community studies"-studies of library training in different nations and the states of the United States, arranged alphabetically.)
  - Hazeltine Books
    - 012 Miscellaneous (Box 79)
    - 015 Elementary Bibliography (Box 79)
    - 016 Bibliography (Box 79)
    - 016-016.2
      - Bibliography (Box 79)
      - Philosophy (Box 79)
      - Religion (Box 79)
    - 016.3-016.37 Sociology (Box 79)
    - 016.394
      - Holidays (Box 79)
      - Birthdays (Box 79)
      - Anniversaries (Box 79)
    - 016.4-016.6
      - Philology (Box 79)
      - Science (Box 79)
      - Useful Arts (Box 80)
    - 016.7-016-77 Art (Box 80)
    - 016.78 Music (Box 80)
    - 016.8 Literature (Box 80)
    - 016.9 History (Box 81)
    - 016.91-016.92 Hartford Public Library (Box 81)
    - 020.5-020-6 Library Associations. Library Periodicals (Box 81)
    - 020.7 Library Schools (Box 81)
    - 021-022 Foundations & Government; branches and delivery stations (Box 81)
    - 022 Library Buildings--Plans (Box 82)
    - 022 Library Buildings--Notes (Box 82)
    - 023-024 Government & Services; regulations for readers (Box 82)
    - 025.1 Executive (Box 82)
    - 025.2 Accession Notes, blanks (Box 83)
    - 025.2 Accession Notes and samples (Box 83)
    - 025.3 Cataloging, cataloging rules (Box 83)
    - 025.3 Advanced Cataloging (Box 84)
    - 025.4 Classification (Box 84)
    - 025.6 Loan Department, blanks (Box 84)
    - 025.7 Binding and Repair (Box 84)
    - 025.8 Shelf Department blanks (Box 85)
    - 027-027.6 Libraries (Box 85)
    - 028 Book collection (Box 85)
    - 028.5 Children’s Reading (Box 85)
    - 029.1-029.3 Methods and labor savers (Box 85)
    - 029.5 Indexing (Box 85)
    - 029.6 Printing (Box 86)
    - 367-392 Miscellaneous (Box 86)
    - 500-600 Science, useful arts (Box 86)
    - 900 History (Box 86)
  - Oversized Materials
    In two oversized boxes
    - Portraits of Librarians (Alumni and Others) (Box Oversized Box)
    - New York State Library School Building Interior Views (Box Oversized Box)
  - Photographs of Prominent Librarians
    - American Library Association, 1886 (Box 76)
    - Bowker, Richard R. (Box 76)
    - Coe, Ellen M. (Box 76)
    - Cutter, Charles A. (Box 76)
    - Dewey, Melvil (Box 76)
    - Larned, Joseph (Box 76)
    - Nelson, C. Alexander (Box 76)
    - Peoples, William T. (Box 76)
    - Poole, William F. (Box 76)
    - Spofford, A.R. (Box 76)
  - Student Records, A-Z
    - A-Bi (Box 55)
    - Bi-Ch (Box 56)
    - Cl-Dz (Box 57)
    - E-Gilbert (Box 58)
    - Gilchrist-Hazeltine (Box 59)
    - Hermans-Jz (Box 60)
    - K-Lz (Box 61)
    - Mac-Metz (Box 62)
    - Middleton-Noyes (Box 63)
    - O’Brien-Proudfoot (Box 64)
    - Pulliam-Rowse (Box 65)
    - Toys-Snyder (Box 66)
    - Spafford-Tz (Box 67)
    - U-Wiggin (Box 68)
    - Wigginton-Z (Box 69)
- Series IV: 2005 Addition
  - Card Files on:
    - Alumni lectures, etc.--Bishop-Richardson (Box 4)
    - Alumni publications for annual printed lists, such as the Library School newsletter (Box 4)
    - Bibliography of alumni of the New York State Library School
      - Abbot-Fenton (Box 1)
      - Ferguson-Loomis (Box 2)
      - Lord-Stockham (Box 3)
      - Stange-Yust (Box 4)
    - Bibliography of faculty of the New York State Library School--Biscoe-Williams (Box 4)
    - Buildings planned wholly or in part by alumni of the New York State Library School--Anderson-Yust
      - 1913-1918 (Box 4)
      - 1919-1926 (Box 5)
    - Personal book plates of alumni--Adsit-Sutliff (Box 4)
    - Publications of the School of Library Service, New York State Library School, Library School of the New York Public Library, Foreign, and Miscellaneous (Box 5)